A Guide to the Elizabeth Smith collection of Virginia ERA Ratification Council records, 1970-2002
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Elizabeth Smith collection of Virginia ERA Ratification Council records, 1970-2002
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 425
8.42 linear feet
Smith, Elizabeth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Smith in 2009.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series: Series 1: Organizational records, 1972-1996; Series 2: Pro-ERA Organizations, 1971-2002; Series 3: Subject Files, 1970-1996; Series 4: Clippings, 1971-1996.
Biographical / Historical Information
Elizabeth Smith served as executive director the Virginia Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council, and she continued to collect materials pertaining to the amendment throughout her time with the Council and in the years following.
The Virginia Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council was a coalition of multiple Virginia organizations brought together by the shared goal of advocating for the ratification of the amendment by Virginia's legislature. The Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) states that "equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex." It was approved by the House of Representatives and the US Senate, and then submitted to the states for ratification in 1972. As of October 2018, the Virginia legislature has yet to ratify the ERA.
Content Description
This collection consists of materials acquired by Elizabeth Smith and includes a large quantity of materials created by or concerning the Virginia Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council. Also included within this collection are items from a number of other organizations such as the National Organization for Women (NOW), American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), Homemakers for the ERA (HERA), the National Women's Party (NWP) and many other pro-ERA organizations of the time. The collection also holds materials documenting the anti-ERA voice of the same era. Materials found in the collection include reports, correspondence, minutes, agendas, printed materials, educational materials, lobbying materials, event ephemera, speeches, and a substantial quantity of clippings. The collection's contents illuminate the efforts of the Virginia Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council and other organizations to advocate for the ratification of the Equal Rights Amendment during the latter decades of the twentieth century.
Women -- Political activity -- Virginia -- Richmond.; Equal rights amendments -- Sources -- Virginia; Women political activists -- Archives -- Virginia; Women's rights -- History -- 20th century -- Southern States; Smith, Elizabeth
- Series 1: Organizational records, 1972-1996
  - Agendas and meeting minutes, 1974-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Bylaws, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coalition building, circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Election law violation report - Larry Pratt, Virginia House of Delegates, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Electoral activities, 1977-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - ERA Summit, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Essay contest, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Essays and speeches, 1974-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Events, 1974-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Executive committee rosters, 1978-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Finances, 1974-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Forms and mailers, 1978-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gala, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Informational flyers and pamphlets, 1974-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Initiative planning, 1976-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Interfaith Task Force, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jean Hellmuth materials, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jean Stapleton cassette tape, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Legislative strategies, 1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Legislator's kit, 1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mailing lists, 1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Member and attendance lists, 1976-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda, 1976-1982, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 1973-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Notecards, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes, 1976-1996, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Organizational overviews, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, 1978-1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Prayer breakfast, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Press releases, 1975-1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ratification updates, 1974, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Referendum materials, 1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Research and Education Fund, 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Resolutions, 1975-1977, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Richmond area ERA YES campaign, 1975-1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Speakers' Bureau, 1976-1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Steering committee, 1977-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Supporters' handbook, circa 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Supporters of ERA lists, 1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Training materials, 1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Vigil preparations, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Vigils, 1979-1995, 2001 undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Virginia legislature, 1974-1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - Virginia State Library records transfer, 1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Volunteers, 1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Pro-ERA Organizations, 1971-2002
  - American Association of University Women, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1975-1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Bar Associations, 1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Business and Professional Women's Clubs, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - California Commission on the Status of Women, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Catholics Act for ERA, 1976-1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Citizens' Advisory Council on the Status of Women, 1966-1976, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Common Cause of Virginia, 1977, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Congressional Union, 1980, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Democratic National Committee, 1976-1981, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - ERAmerica, 1976-1981 (Box 6, Folder 10-11, Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Homemakers' Equal Rights Association, 1975-1982, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Institute for Studies in Equality Equal Rights Monitor, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - International Women's Year, 1976-1991, undated (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - League of Women Voters, 1972-1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - League of Women Voters of Virginia and local chapters, 1975-1984 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, 1976-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - National Organization for Women, 1971-1992, undated (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - National Organization for Women - Richmond, 1976-1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - National Organization for Women - Virginia, 1974-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - National Women's Party, 1978-2002, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - National Women's Political Caucus, 1979-1990 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - National Women's Political Caucus of Virginia, 1981-1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Religious Committee for ERA, 1975-1982, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Republican National Committee, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Reston ERA Coalition, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Richmond Committee on the Concerns for Women, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Richmond Council of Women's Organizations, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - United Methodist Church, 1978, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - United States Commission on Civil Rights, 1975-1985 (Box 9, Folder 8- 10)
  - University of Virginia Institute of Government, 1974-1984 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Council of Churches, 1981-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Education Association, 1980-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Virginia ERA Ratification Project, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Women Attorneys Association, 1981-1986 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Virgina Women's Meeting, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Virginians for the Equal Rights Amendment Political Action Committee, 1977-1979, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Women and the Constitution Institute, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Women's Action Alliance, 1978-1979, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Women's Bureau, 1980-1984 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Women's Center of Richmond, 1974, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Women's Equity Action League, 1976-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1972-1989, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Women's Round Table, 1979-1989 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Young Women's Christian Association, 1978-1989, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Series 3: Subject Files, 1970-1996
  - Abortion, 1976-1987 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Anti-ERA flyers and pamphlets, 1972-1982 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Anti-ERA rebuttal information, 1977-1981, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Background information on the ERA, 1973-1992, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Buttons, bracelet, and bear ornament, undated (Box 20)
  - Christian denominations, 1975-1982, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Credit access, 1975-1980 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Education, 1974-1981, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Equal Employment, 1972-1989, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Essays and speeches, 1972-1987, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Extension and rescission of ratification, 1973-1981, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Family, 1975-1986, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Informational flyers and pamphlets, 1975-1989, undated (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
  - Informational flyers and pamphlets - Virginia, 1976-1985, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Labor, 1976-1983 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Language, 1976, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Lobbying, 1977-1981 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Military draft, 1970-1981, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Music and religious services, 1978-1988, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Pay Equity, 1981-1987, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Pennant, sashes, and textiles, undated (Box 19)
  - Phyllis Schlafly Report, 1973-1981 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Posters, 1975-2002, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Property rights, marriage, and divorce, 1978-1982, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Resource bibliographies and lists, 1973, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Retirement, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Sexual assault and domestic violence, 1977-1985 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Socialism, 1978-1979, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - State materials on ERA, 1972-1995 (Box 13, Folder 11-12)
  - Unitarian Universalism, 1976-1985 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - United States Congress, 1976-1990, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Virginia legislature, 1976-1983, undated (Box 14, Folder 3-6, Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Virginia legislature - ERA Task Force, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Military Institute case, 1973-1996, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Virginia State Board of Elections, 1979, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Series 4: Clippings, 1971-1996
  - Articles, 1976-1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1971-1996, undated (Box 15:6-7, boxes 16-18: all folders)